<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A breefe catechisme so necessarie and easie to be learned euen of the symple sort that whosoeuer can not or vvyll not attayne to the same, is not to be counted a good Christian, much lesse to be admitted to the Supper of the Lorde. It standeth of three partes. ...</title>
            <title>Breefe catechisme so necessarie and easie to be learned even of the symple sort.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1576</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18157</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4798</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109782</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845427</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845427</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10324</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18157)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10324)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 189:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A breefe catechisme so necessarie and easie to be learned euen of the symple sort that whosoeuer can not or vvyll not attayne to the same, is not to be counted a good Christian, much lesse to be admitted to the Supper of the Lorde. It standeth of three partes. ...</title>
                  <title>Breefe catechisme so necessarie and easie to be learned even of the symple sort.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Hugh Singleton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1576.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Leaf A2 begins: Art thou not a subiect and a seruant vnto the Almyghtie God, and Lord of Heauen and Earth?.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10324:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 140 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:10324:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 140 -->
            <p>A breefe Catechiſme ſo neceſſarie and eaſie to be learned euen of the ſymple ſort, that whoſoeuer can not or vvyll not attayne to the ſame, is not to be counted a good Chriſtian, much leſſe to be admitted to the Supper of the Lorde.</p>
            <p>It standeth of three partes.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The firſt ſheweth howe miſerable all men are of them ſelues.</item>
               <item>2. The ſeconde, howe happy they are that rightly beleeue in Chriſt.</item>
               <item>3. The thirde, what duties they owe vnto God, for his greate merye to wardes them in Chriſt Ieſus.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1576.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON.</hi> Printed by Hugh Singleton.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:10324:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 141 -->
            <q>
               <bibl>1. PETER. 3.15.16.</bibl>
               <p>Sanctifye the Lorde God in your heartes, and be ready alwayes to geue an aunſwere to euery man that aſketh you a reaſon of the hope that is in you.</p>
               <p>And that with meekeneſſe and reacrence, hauing a good conſcience, that when they ſpeake euill of you as of euill dooers, they may be aſhamed which blame your good conuerſation in Christe.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:10324:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 141 -->
            <head>THE FIRST PART.</head>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Rt thou not a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect and a ſeruant vnto the Almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, and Lord of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and Earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Aunſwere.</label>
I acknowledge and yeeld my ſelfe for euer to be his ſubiect and ſeruaunt.<note place="margin">Exod. 20.2. Ioſ. 24.15.24. Rom. 12.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>Hath God giuen foorth any lawes, whereby his ſubiectes ſhoulde be wel ruled and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſvvere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The holy ſcriptures are Gods ſtatures and lawes,<note place="margin">Hebru. 1.12. Luk. 16.29.31 Dent. 4.13.</note> wherein he declareth his wyll and pleaſure, the generall ſumme and effect whereof is breefely ſet foorth vnto vs in the tenne Commaundementes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10324:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 142 -->
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>Rehearſe the tenne Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">i. GOD ſpake all theſe wordes and ſayd,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.3.</note> I am the Lorde thy GOD, thou ſhalt haue none other gods but me.</p>
            <p n="2">ii. Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen image, nor the likeneſſe of any thing that is in heauen aboue, or in the earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, or in the waters vnder the earth, thou ſhalt not bowe downe to them, nor worſhip them, for I the Lorde am a ielious God, and will vifite the ſinnes of the fathers vpon the chyldren, vnto the third and fourth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of them that hate me, and ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vnto thouſandes in them that loue me, and keepe my commaundements.</p>
            <p n="3">iii. Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lorde thy GOD in vayne, for the Lorde will not holde him giltles, that taketh his name in vayne.</p>
            <p n="4">iiii. Remember that thou keepe holy the Sabboth day, ſixe dayes ſhalt thou laboure and doe all that thou haſt to doe: but the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth day is the Sabboth of the Lorde the GOD, in it thou ſhalt doe no manner of worke, thou nor thy ſonne, thy daughter,
<pb facs="tcp:10324:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 142 -->thy man ſeruant, nor thy maydſeruant, thy cattell, nor the ſtraunger that is within thy gates: for in ſixe dayes the Lorde made Heauen and Earth, the Sea and all that in them is, wherefore the Lorde bleſſed the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth day, and hallowed it.</p>
            <p n="5">v. Honour thy Father and thy Mother, that thy dayes may be long in the lande, which the Lorde thy GOD geueth thee.</p>
            <p n="6">vi. Thou ſhalt doe no murder.</p>
            <p n="7">vii. Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie.</p>
            <p n="8">viii. Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
            <p n="9">ix. Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt thy neyghbour.</p>
            <p n="10">x. Thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbours houſe, thou ſhalt not couet thy neyghbours wyfe, nor his ſeruaunt, nor his mayde, nor his Oxe, nor his Aſſe, nor any thing that is his.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>Are you able to keepe all theſe lawes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſvvere</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Euery man daily breaketh them in thought,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 19.12. Eccleſi. 7.22. 1. Iohn. 1.8.</note> word, and deede.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>What is the danger of brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="tcp:10324:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 143 -->any of theſe lawes and commaundementes of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Aunſvvere,</label>
            </p>
            <p>The iuſt wages and puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of breaking the leaſt of Gods holy lawes,<note place="margin">Math. 5.19.22.</note> yea if it were but once in all my life,<note place="margin">Rom. 6 23.</note> and in thought onely:<note place="margin">Ga<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. 3.10.</note> is the loſſe of Gods fauour, the purchaſing of his heauye diſpleaſure:<note place="margin">Iames. 2.10.</note> which bringeth euerlaſting death both of ſoule and body.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <head>THE SECOND PART.</head>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>Howe ſhall you eſcape this great daunger, and feareful punishment of your ſinnes. Wyll not your good deedes ſerue to make ſome amends to GOD for your il deedes, and ſo deliuer you from this puniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10324:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 143 -->
               <label>Aunſvvere.</label>
My good deedes will not helpe to ſaue me from this puniſhment, nor any thing els,<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.9. Actes. 4.1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Gala. 2.21.</note> but onely the deedes of Ieſus Chriſt hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered me.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>How hath Jeſus Christ ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and deliuered you from this great punishment of your ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Aunſvvere.</label>
Ieſus Chriſte hath deliuered me from the puniſhment of my ſinne,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cala. 3.13. Eſai. 53.5.</note> becauſe he being both GOD and Man,<note place="margin">Col. 1.19.20.</note> hath ſuffered all the puniſhment which my ſinnes deſerued,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.24.</note> and hath fulfilled the lawe of God perfectly for me,<note place="margin">Rom 4.25.</note> and thereby hath reſtored me for euer to the loue and fauour of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>Are all then ſaued by this ſuffering &amp; death of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Aunſvvere.</label>
Only they are ſaued by Chriſt,<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.16.3.</note> who beleeue that he hath doone all thinges touching ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, not onely for other,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.20. Ioh. 1.20.22.</note> but alſo euen for
<pb facs="tcp:10324:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 144 -->them ſelues, the effect of which faith is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in the Creede.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>Rehearſe the Creede.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Aunſvvere.</label>
I beleeue in God the Father Almighty ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of Heauen and Earth.<note place="margin">Iohn. 14 1.</note> And in Ieſus Chriſt his onely ſonne our Lorde. Whiche was conceyued by the holy Ghoſt, horne of the Virgin Marie. Suffered vnder Ponce Pilate, was crucified, dead, and buryed, he deſcended into Hell. The third day he roſe againe from the dead. He aſſended into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and ſitteth at the right hand of God the Father Almightie. From thence ſhall he come to iudge the quicke and the dead. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue in the holy Ghoſt. The holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church. The Communion of Saintes. The forgeueneſſe of ſinnes. The reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the body. And the life euerlaſting A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>By what meanes haue we ſuch a true fayth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſvvere.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 16.17. Epheſi 6.23. 2. Cor. 4.13. Mark. 9.24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is the gyft of GOD.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10324:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 144 -->
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>How dooth God woorke this fayth in vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Aunſvvere</label>
By the preaching of the woord of God.<note place="margin">Rom. 1.12.17. Rom. 10.4.17. Iames. 1.21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>Is this fayth fully framed, and made ſtrong in vs at the fyrſt, or in one houre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Aunſvvere.</label>
Fayth is increaſed by little and little,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.17. Galat. 4.19. Epheſi. 4.11.12.13. 1. Theſſa. 5.19.20.</note> and made ſtrong in vs by the diligent hearing of the worde of God, and by the vſe of his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>How many Sacraments are there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Aunſvvere.</label>
There are two Sacraments, Baptiſme,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.11. 1. Cor. 10.2.3. Math. 21.25. Matth. 28.19. Matth. 26.2.6 Acts. 2.26.</note> and the Supper of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>What benifite haue you by Baptiſme, and to what end ſerueth it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10324:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 145 -->
               <label>Aunſvvere.</label>
By Baptiſme the holy Ghoſt aſſureth me,<note place="margin">Acts 22.16.</note> that as my bodye is ſprinkled with water, ſo my ſoule,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.21.</note> by the bloodſhedding of Chriſt, is ſprinckled and waſhed from all the guilte and puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of my ſinnes,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2.12.</note> and alſo herby I profeſſe my ſelfe to dye with Chriſte, as concerning ſinne,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.4.</note> and liue in him as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>To what ende ſerueth the Supper of the Lorde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Aunſvvere.</label>
In the Supper of the Lorde,<note place="margin">Luke. 22.19.20. 1. Pet. 10.16.</note> I am by the ſpirite of GOD aſſured, that as the breade broken, and the wine poured out be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto me,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.23.34</note> euen ſo was the body of Chriſt broken, and his bloude ſhed, as a full recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence to God for my ſinnes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <head>THE THIRD PART.</head>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>For aſmuch then as God of his infinite loue, hath geuen his owne ſonne, to raunſome
<pb facs="tcp:10324:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 146 -->vs from the power of ſinne, death, and hell, to aduaunce vs to the honour of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and heires of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: ſeing it pleaſeth him to geue vs fayth, and daylye to nouriſh and encreaſe it in vs more and more: by his woorde and Sacramentes, by the which fayth we lay hold vpon Chriſte, and make him with al his merits and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures our owne: ſo that nowe not only alour ſinnes are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued from vs, but alſo his righteouſnes, holineſſe, and perfection, is accounted ours
<pb facs="tcp:10324:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 146 -->before GOD: Do you not thinke that we are very depe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly bound vnto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſvvers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes veryly. I am ſo much bounde to God,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 8.5. Pſalm. 116.12 Rom. 12.1.</note> that al my life ought to be a continual thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes to his Maieſtie, for his great mercie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quueſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is then this doctrine whiche ſheweth vs that we are ſaued by Jeſus Chriſt only, &amp; not by our owne woorkes, any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of wicked lyfe, as the Papiſts ſlaunder it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Aunſvvere.</label>
This doctrine is no occaſion of wicked lyfe,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1. 1. Iohn. 2.1. Rom. 6.1. Titus. 2.11.12.</note> but the greateſt reaſon to perſwade men to be diligent and zealous in good woorkes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>Are there no other good deedes required of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<pb facs="tcp:10324:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 147 -->but giuing of almes, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting the ſycke, buylding of ſchooles, and houſes for the poore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Aunſvvere.</label>
               <note n="a." place="margin">Math. 6.2. 1. Cor. 13.3.</note> As theſe are good deedes, and ſuch as highly pleaſe God, being doone in ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as the worde of God dooth teache vs:<note n="b." place="margin">Exo. 20.3.4. Math. 22.36.</note> So are there many other much more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent then theſe: as the pure worſhipping of God both with the ſoule and body:<note n="c." place="margin">Iob. 13.15.</note> tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and dependidg of his good prouidence both in proſperitie and aduerſitie:<note n="d." place="margin">Luk. 10.42.</note> hearing of his holy worde:<note n="e." place="margin">Theſ. 5.11.14. Hebre. 3.13. Coloſ. 3.16. Iacob. 5.20.</note> exhortations and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions one to an other, eſpecially to ſuch as we haue ſpeciall charge ouer:<note n="f." place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.16. Pſalm. 50.14.15.</note> prayſing God for all his mercies, and continuall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifites powred vpon vs: and laſt of all,<note n="g." place="margin">Iudges. 20. Ephe. 6.18. Pſalm. 50.15. Actes. 4.24.</note> faythfull prayers for all ſuch thinges as we ſtand in neede of.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>To whom ough we to make our prayers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Aunſvvere.</label>
We muſt pray to our louing and Almighty GOD alone, and to none but him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10324:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 147 -->
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>What thinges ought we to pray for.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Aunſvvere.</label>
We muſt praye,<note place="margin">Actes. 4.29. Ephe. 6.18.19.</note> not onely for all thinges needefull for our ſelues and the churche of GOD, but eſpecially for thoſe thinges whiche appertayne to the ſetting foorth of the glory of God, euen as we are taught in the Lordes prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>Rehearſe the Lordes pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Aunſvere.</label>
Our father which art in Heauen, hallowed be thy name.<note place="margin">Math. 6.9.</note> Thy kingdome come. Thy wyll be done in Earth, as it i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in Heauen. Geue vs this day our daly breade. And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue vs our treſpaſſes, as we forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs. And leade vs not into temptation But deliuer vs from euyll Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>How may we be aſsured that God wyl heare vs, ſeeing we
<pb facs="tcp:10324:8"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 147 -->are ſinners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Aunſvvere.</label>
Becauſe we offer vp our prayers,<note place="margin">Iohn. 16.29. 1. Iohn. 2.1. 1. Pet. 2.5.</note> not in our own name, nor in the name of any creature but of the ſonne of God our Sauiour, who is alwayes in the preſence of God, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate his maieſtie for vs, his poore Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <trailer type="illustration">
               <figure/>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
